Have you heard the news?
هل سمعتم الأخبار؟
We're in a clean energy revolution.
نحنُ في ثورة طاقة نظيفة.
And where I live in Berkeley, California,
وحيثُ أعيش في بيركيلي، بكاليفورنيا،
it seems like every day I see a new roof with new solar panels going up,
يبدو أنني أرى كل يوم سطح جديد فوقه ألواح شمسية جديدة،
electric car in the driveway.
وسيارة كهربائية في ممر المنازل.
Germany sometimes gets half its power from solar,
تحصل ألمانيا أحيانًا على نصف طاقتها من الشمس،
and India is now committed to building 10 times more solar
وتلتزم الهند اليوم ببناء الطاقة الشمسية أكثر بعشر مرات
than we have in California,
مما لدينا في كاليفورنيا،
by the year 2022.
بحلول عام 2020.
Even nuclear seems to be making a comeback.
حتى يبدو أن الطاقة النووية تعود مجددًا.
Bill Gates is in China working with engineers,
حيث يعملُ بيل جيتس مع المهندسين في الصين
there's 40 different companies that are working together
وهناك 40 شركة مختلفة تعمل معاً
to try to race to build the first reactor that runs on waste,
في محاولة للسباق لبناء أول مفاعل يعملُ على النفايات،
that can't melt down
التي لا يمكن أن تذوب
and is cheaper than coal.
وأرخص من الفحم.
And so you might start to ask:
وربما قد تبدأوا في التساؤل:
Is this whole global warming problem
هل مشكلة الاحترار العالمي ككل
going to be a lot easier to solve than anybody imagined?
ستكون أكثر سهولة للحل مما يتوقع أي شخص؟
That was the question we wanted to know,
كان هذا هو السؤال الذي أردنا معرفته،
so my colleagues and I decided to take a deep dive into the data.
لذلك قررتُ وزملائي الغوص العميق داخل البيانات.
We were a little skeptical of some parts
كنا نشك قليلاً في بعض الأجزاء
of the clean energy revolution story,
من قصة ثورة الطاقة النظيفة،
but what we found really surprised us.
ولكن ما وجدناه أدهشنا في الحقيقة.
The first thing is that clean energy has been increasing.
الشيء الأول هو أن الطاقة النظيفة في ازدياد.
This is electricity from clean energy sources over the last 20 years.
هذه هي الكهرباء من مصادر الطاقة النظيفة على مدى أكثر من 20 عامًا مضت.
But when you look at the percentage of global electricity
لكن عندما تنظرون إلى نسبة الكهرباء المنتجة في العالم
from clean energy sources,
من مصادر الطاقة النظيفة،
it's actually been in decline from 36 percent to 31 percent.
فإنها في الحقيقة قد تقلصت من 36% إلى 31%.
And if you care about climate change,
وإذا كنتم تهتمون بالتغير المناخي،
you've got to go in the opposite direction
عليكم الذهاب في الاتجاه المعاكس
to 100 percent of our electricity from clean energy sources,
إلى 100% من الكهرباء لدينا من مصادر الطاقة النظيفة،
as quickly as possible.
بأسرع ما يمكن.
Now, you might wonder,
الآن، قد تتساءلون،
"Come on, how much could five percentage points of global electricity be?"
"هيا، كم يمكن لـِ 5% نقطة من كهرباء العالم أن تكون؟"
Well, it turns out to be quite a bit.
حسنًا، لقد تبين أنها قليلة نسبيًا.
It's the equivalent of 60 nuclear plants
إنها تعادلُ 60% من المحطات النووية
the size of Diablo Canyon, California's last nuclear plant,
حجم محطة توليد الكهرباء الأخيرة في كاليفورنيا "ديابلو كانيون"،
or 900 solar farms the size of Topaz,
أو 900 حقل للطاقة الشمسية حجم محطة توباز،
which is one of the biggest solar farms in the world,
التي هي واحدة من أكبر حقول الطاقة الشمسية في العالم،
and certainly our biggest in California.
وهي بالتأكيد أكبر ما لدينا في كاليفورنيا.
A big part of this is simply that fossil fuels are increasing
حسناً، الجزء الكبير من هذا هو ببساطة أن الوقود الأحفوري في تزايد
faster than clean energy.
أسرع من الطاقة النظيفة.
And that's understandable.
وهذا مفهوم.
There's just a lot of poor countries
هناك الكثير من الدول الفقيرة
that are still using wood and dung and charcoal
التي ما زالت تستخدم الخشب والروث والفحم
as their main source of energy,
كمصدر رئيسي للطاقة،
and they need modern fuels.
وهم بحاجة إلى الوقود الحديث.
But there's something else going on,
ولكن يجري هناك شيئاً آخر،
which is that one of those clean energy sources in particular
والذي هو أن أحد مصادر تلك الطاقة النظيفة على وجه الخصوص
has actually been on the decline in absolute terms,
قد انخفضت حقًا بشكل مطلق تماماً
not just relatively.
وليس نسبيًا فقط.
And that's nuclear.
وهذه هي الطاقة النووية.
You can see its generation has declined seven percent
يمكنكم رؤية أن جيل الطاقة النووية قد انخفضت 7%
over the last 10 years.
على مدى السنوات العشر الأخيرة.
Now, solar and wind have been making huge strides,
الآن، تخطو الطاقة الشمسية وطاقة الرياح خطوات كبيرة،
so you hear a lot of talk about how it doesn't really matter,
فلقد سمعتم الكثير من الحديث حول كيف أن هذه ليست مهمة حقًا،
because solar and wind is going to make up the difference.
لأن الطاقة الشمسية وطاقة الرياح ستعوضُ الفرق.
But the data says something different.
لكن تقول البيانات شيئاً مختلفًا.
When you combine all the electricity from solar and wind,
عندما تجمعون كل الكهرباء من الطاقة الشمسية وطاقة الرياح،
you see it actually barely makes up half of the decline from nuclear.
فإنها بالكاد تشكلُ نصف الإنخفاض من الطاقة النووية في الواقع.
Let's take a closer look in the United States.
دعونا ننظرُ عن كثب في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية.
Over the last couple of years -- really 2013, 2014 --
على مدى العامين الماضيين-- في عامي 2013 و 2014--
we prematurely retired four nuclear power plants.
قمنا بإحالة أربعة معامل للطاقة النووية للتقاعد.
They were almost entirely replaced with fossil fuels,
وتم استبدالهم بالكامل بالوقود الأحفوري،
and so the consequence was that we wiped out
ولذلك، كانت النتيجة أننا مسحنا
almost as much clean energy electricity that we get from solar.
تقريبًا كل كهرباء الطاقة النظيفة التي نحصلُ عليها من الطاقة الشمسية.
And it's not unique to us.
وهي ليست فريدة من نوعها بالنسبة إلينا.
People think of California as a clean energy and climate leader,
يعتقدُ الناس أن كاليفورنيا رائدة في الطاقة النظيفة والمناخ،
but when we looked at the data,
ولكن عندما نظرنا في البيانات،
what we found is that, in fact,
في الواقع، ما وجدناه هو أن،
California reduced emissions more slowly than the national average,
قلّصت كاليفورنيا الانبعاثات ببطء أكثر من المعدل القومي،
between 2000 and 2015.
ما بين عامي 2000 و 2015.
What about Germany?
ماذا عن ألمانيا؟
They're doing a lot of clean energy.
إنهم يعملون الكثير من الطاقة النظيفة.
But when you look at the data,
لكن عندما تنظرون إلى البيانات،
German emissions have actually been going up since 2009,
فالانبعاثات في ألمانيا في تصاعد مستمر منذ عام 2008،
and there's really not anybody who's going to tell you
ولا يوجد في الحقيقة أي شخص يمكنه أن يقول لكم
that they're going to meet their climate commitments in 2020.
بأنهم قادرون على تلبية الالتزامات المناخية في عام 2020.
The reason isn't hard to understand.
فليس من الصعب فهم السبب.
Solar and wind provide power about 10 to 20 percent of the time,
توفر الشمس والرياح طاقة تعادل حوالي 10%إلى 20% من الوقت ،
which means that when the sun's not shining,
مما يعني أنه عندما لا تشرقُ الشمس،
the wind's not blowing,
ولا تهبُ الرياح،
you still need power for your hospitals,
فأنتم ما زلتم بحاجة لطاقة من أجل مستشفياتكم،
your homes, your cities, your factories.
ومنازلكم ومدنكم ومصانعكم.
And while batteries have made some really cool improvements lately,
وبينما صنعت البطاريات بعض التحسينات الرائعة حقاً في الآونة الأخيرة،
the truth is, they're just never going to be as efficient
فالحقيقة، أنها لن تكون فعالة مطلقًا
as the electrical grid.
كما الشبكة الكهربائية.
Every time you put electricity into a battery and take it out,
ففي كل مرة تضعون الكهرباء في البطارية وتنزعونها،
you lose about 20 to 40 percent of the power.
فإنكم تخسرون 20% إلى 40% من الطاقة.
That's why when, in California,
لهذا السبب عندما يكون الأمر في كاليفورنيا،
we try to deal with all the solar we've brought online --
نحاول التعامل مع جميع خطوط الكهرباء المتولدة من الشمس--
we now get about 10 percent of electricity from solar --
فإننا نحصلُ حاليًا على 10% من الكهرباء من الطاقة الشمسية --
when the sun goes down, and people come home from work
عندما تغربُ الشمس، ويحضر الناس إلى منازلهم من العمل
and turn on their air conditioners and their TV sets,
ويشغلون أجهزة التبريد والتلفزة لديهم،
and every other appliance in the house,
وكل الأجهزة الأُخرى في المنزل،
we need a lot of natural gas backup.
نحتاج إلى الكثير من احتياطي الغاز الطبيعي.
So what we've been doing
لذلك، ما قمنا بعمله
is stuffing a lot of natural gas into the side of a mountain.
هو تكديس الكثير من الغاز الطبيعي بجانب أحد الجبال.
And that worked pretty well for a while,
وعمل ذلك جيدًا لفترة من الزمن،
but then late last year, it sprung a leak.
لكن لاحقاً، وفي السنة الاخيرة، ظهر تسرب.
This is Aliso Canyon.
هذا هو أليسو كانيون.
So much methane gas was released,
تسرب الكثير من غاز الميثان،
it was the equivalent of putting half a million cars on the road.
وكان يعادلُ وضع نصف مليون حافلة على الطريق.
It basically blew through all of our climate commitments for the year.
واحترق في الأساس خلال كل إلتزاماتنا المناخي لذلك العام.
Well, what about India?
حسنًا، ماذا عن الهند؟
Sometimes you have to go places to really get the right data,
عليكم أحياناً الذهاب إلى الأماكن للحصول على البيانات الصحيحة حقًا،
so we traveled to India a few months ago.
لذلك، سافرنا إلى الهند قبل عدة أشهر.
We met with all the top officials -- solar, nuclear, the rest --
قابلنا كل رؤساء الطاقة الشمسية والنووية وغيرهم من المسؤولين،
and what they told us is,
وما أخبرونا به هو،
"We're actually having more serious problems
"لدينا في الحقيقة مشاكل جدية أكثر
than both Germany and California.
من كلٍ من ألمانيا وكاليفورنيا.
We don't have backup; we don't have all the natural gas.
وليس لدينا احتياطات، وليس لدينا كل الغاز الطبيعي.
And that's just the start of it.
وهذه هي البداية فقط.
Say we want to get to 100 gigawatts by 2022.
قلنا أننا نريدُ الحصول على 100 جيجاواط بحلول 2022.
But last year we did just five,
لكننا حصلنا على خمسة فقط في العام الماضي،
and the year before that, we did five."
وعلى خمسة أخرى في العام الذي سبقه."
So, let's just take a closer look at nuclear.
لذلك، دعونا نلقي نظرة فاحصة على الطاقة النووية.
The United Nations Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change
قامت اللجنة الدولية للتغيرات المناخية التابعة للأمم المتحدة
has looked at the carbon content of all these different fuels,
بفحص محتوى الكربون لكل أنواع الوقود،
and nuclear comes out really low -- it's actually lower even than solar.
وكان النووي المنبعث منخفض حقاً-- إنه في الواقع أقل حتى من الطاقة الشمسية.
And nuclear obviously provides a lot of power --
وتوفر الطاقة النووية كما هو واضح الكثير من الطاقة --
24 hours a day, seven days a week.
24 ساعة يومياً، 7 أيام أسبوعيًا.
During a year, a single plant can provide power 92 percent of the time.
يستطيع معمل واحد توفير طاقة 92% من الوقت خلال السنة.
What's interesting is that when you look at countries
ما هو مثير للإهتمام هو أنه عندما تنظرون إلى الدول
that have deployed different kinds of clean energies,
التي نشرت أنواع مختلفة من الطاقة النظيفة،
there's only a few that have done so
قامت بذلك فقط عدد من الدول
at a pace consistent with dealing with the climate crisis.
في وتيرة متناسقة بالتعامل مع أزمة المناخ.
So nuclear seems like a pretty good option,
لذلك، تبدو الطاقة النووية اختيار جيد جدًا،
but there's this big problem with it,
لكن يوجد هناك مشكلة كبيرة باستخدامه،
which all of you, I'm sure, are aware of,
وأنا متأكد أن جميعكم على دراية فيها،
which is that people really don't like it.
وهي أن الناس لا يحبون الطاقة النووية حقًا.
There was a study, a survey done of people around the world,
كانت هناك دراسة ومعاينة تم القيام بها للناس حول العالم،
not just in the United States or Europe,
ليس فقط في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية وأوروبا،
about a year and a half ago.
قبل حوالي عام ونصف.
And what they found
وما وجدوه
is that nuclear is actually one of the least popular forms of energy.
هو أن الطاقة النووية هي في الحقيقة واحدة من أقل الأشكال الشائعة للطاقة.
Even oil is more popular than nuclear.
حتى النفط هو أكثر شيوعًا من الطاقة النووية.
And while nuclear kind of edges out coal, the thing is,
وبينما الطاقة النووية تنافسُ طاقة الفحم نوعاً ما، الشيء هو،
people don't really fear coal in the same way they fear nuclear,
الناس لا تهابُ في الحقيقة الفحم بنفس الطريقة التي يهابون فيها الطاقة النووية،
which really operates on our unconscious.
وهذا يدورُ في اللاوعي لدينا.
So what is it that we fear?
لذلك، فما الذي نخشاه؟
There's really three things.
هناك ثلاث مسائل في الحقيقة.
There's the safety of the plants themselves --
هناك سلامة المعامل نفسها --
the fears that they're going to melt down and cause damage;
الخوف من أنه من الممكن أن تصهر وتسبب الضرر؛
there's the waste from them;
هناك النفايات الخارجة منها؛
and there's the association with weapons.
وهناك ما يتعلق بالأسلحة النووية.
And I think, understandably,
وأعتقد أن هذه الأمور مفهومة،
engineers look at those concerns and look for technological fixes.
ينظر المهندسون لهذه المخاوف كما يبحثون من أجل الحلول التقنية
That's why Bill Gates is in China developing advanced reactors.
لهذا السبب فإن بيل جيتس في الصين لتطوير مفاعلات متقدمة.
That's why 40 different entrepreneurs are working on this problem.
ولهذا السبب يعملُ 40 من أصحاب المشاريع المختلفة على هذه المشكلة.
And I, myself, have been very excited about it.
وكنتُ نفسي متحمسًا جدا حول هذا.
We did a report: "How to Make Nuclear Cheap."
أنجزنا تقريراً: "كيفية جعل الطاقة النووية رخيصة."
In particular, the thorium reactor shows a lot of promise.
لا سيما وأن مفاعل الثوريوم يظهر الكثير من النجاح.
So when the climate scientist, James Hansen,
لذلك، عندما سألني خبير المناخ "جيمس هانسن"،
asked if I wanted to go to China with him
إن كنتُ أرغب في الذهاب معه إلى الصين
and look at the Chinese advanced nuclear program,
والنظر في برنامج الصين النووي المتطور،
I jumped at the chance.
فقبلتُ العرض على الفور.
We were there with MIT and UC Berkeley engineers.
كنا هناك مع معهد ماساتشوستس للتكنولوجيا ومهندسي جامعة كاليفورنيا في بيركلي.
And I had in my mind
وكان في ذهني
that the Chinese would be able to do with nuclear
بأن الصينيون سيكونوا قادرين بالتعامل مع النووي
what they did with so many other things --
كما فعلوا مع عدة أشياء أخرى --
start to crank out small nuclear reactors on assembly lines,
البدء في إنتاج مفاعلات نووية صغيرة في خطوط تجميعية،
ship them up like iPhones or MacBooks and send them around the world.
وتصديرها مثل الهواتف النقالة والحواسيب من نوع أبل وإرسالها حول العالم.
I would get one at home in Berkeley.
وسأحصل على واحد في البيت في بيركلي.
But what I found was somewhat different.
لكن ما وجدته هو مختلف نوعًا ما.
The presentations were all very exciting and very promising;
كانت كل عروضهم مثيرة للغاية وواعدة جدًا؛
they have multiple reactors that they're working on.
لديهم العديد من المفاعلات التي يعملون عليها.
The time came for the thorium reactor, and a bunch of us were excited.
حان وقت الحديث عن مفاعل الثوريوم، وكان العديد منا متحمسًا.
They went through the whole presentation, they got to the timeline,
أنجزوا العرض التقديمي بالكامل، ووصلوا إلى الجدول الزمني،
and they said,
وقالوا،
"We're going to have a thorium molten salt reactor
"سننجزُ مفاعل الملح المنصهر بإستخدام الثوريوم كوقود نووي
ready for sale to the world
وسيكون جاهزًا للبيع إلى العالم
by 2040."
بحلول عام 2040."
And I was like, "What?"
وقلتُ، "ماذا؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I looked at my colleagues and I was like,
نظرتُ إلى زملائي وقلت،
"Excuse me --
"لو سمحتم--
can you guys speed that up a little bit?
هل يمكنكم يا رفاق تسريع ذلك قليلًا؟
Because we're in a little bit of a climate crisis right now.
لأننا حاليًا وسط أزمة مناخ.
And your cities are really polluted, by the way."
وبالمناسبة، مدنكم هي في الحقيقة ملوثة."
And they responded back, they were like,
وردوا علي قائلين،
"I'm not sure what you've heard about our thorium program,
"لسنا متأكدين مما سمعته حول برنامجنا لاستخدام الثوريوم،
but we don't have a third of our budget,
لكن ليس لدينا ثلث ميزانيتنا،
and your department of energy hasn't been particularly forthcoming
ولم ترد دائرتكم للطاقة على الأخص
with all that data you guys have on testing reactors."
بكل البيانات التي كانت لديكم يا رفاق حول اختبار المفاعلات."
And I said, "Well, I've got an idea.
وقلت، "حسناً، أنا لدي فكرة.
You know how you've got 10 years where you're demonstrating that reactor?
تعلمون كيف حصلتم على 10 سنوات حيث كنتم تستعرضون هذا المفاعل؟
Let's just skip that part,
دعونا نتخطى هذا الجزء،
and let's just go right to commercializing it.
ودعونا نتجه فقط لتسويقه.
That will save money and time."
وسيوفر ذلك المال والوقت."
And the engineer just looked at me and said,
نظر المهندس لي وقال،
"Let me ask you a question:
"دعني أطرحُ عليك سؤالاً:
Would you buy a car that had never been demonstrated before?"
هل ستقوم بشراء سيارة لم تستعرضها من قبل مطلقًا؟"
So what about the other reactors?
فماذا عن المفاعلات الأخرى؟
There's a reactor that's coming online now, they're starting to sell it.
يوجد هناك مفاعلًا بدأ تشغيله حالياً، وبدأوا في بيعه.
It's a high-temperature gas reactor.
إنه مفاعل غاز ذو درجة حرارة عالية.
It can't melt down.
ولا يمكن صهره.
But it's really big and bulky, that's part of the safety,
ولكنه كبير وضخم حقًا، هذا هو جزء من السلامة،
and nobody thinks it's going to ever get cheaper
ولا يعتقد أحد بأنه سيكون أرخص من أي وقتٍ مضى
than the reactors that we have.
من سعر المفاعلات التي لدينا.
The ones that use waste as fuel are really cool ideas, but the truth is,
فالمفاعلات التي تستخدم النفايات كوقود هي في الحقيقة أفكار رائعة، لكن الحقيقة هي:
we don't actually know how to do that yet.
لا نعرفُ حتى الآن كيفية صُنعها في الحقيقة.
There's some risk that you'll actually make more waste,
يوجد هناك بعض الخطورة بأنكم ستقومون بعمل نفايات أكثر،
and most people think that if you're including
ويعتقد معظم الناس بأنكم إذا شملتم
that waste part of the process,
تلك النفايات كجزء من العملية،
it's just going to make the whole machine a lot more expensive,
وهذا فقط سيجعل الآلة كاملةً أكثر تكلفة،
it's just adding another complicated step.
إنها تضيف فقط خطوة معقدة أخرى.
The truth is,
الحقيقة هي،
there's real questions about how much of that we're going to do.
هناك أسئلة حقيقية حول كم مفاعلاً سنقوم بصنعه.
I mean, we went to India and asked about the nuclear program.
أعني، ذهبنا إلى الهند وسألنا عن البرنامج النووي.
The government said before the Paris climate talks
قالت الحكومة قبل محادثات باريس للتغيرات المناخية
that they were going to do something like 30 new nuclear plants.
بأنهم في طريقهم بعمل شيء مثل بناء 30 معملاً نووياً جديدًا.
But when we got there and interviewed people
وعندما وصلنا هناك وأجرينا مقابلات مع الناس
and even looked at the internal documents,
ونظرنا في الوثائق الداخلية،
they're now saying they're going to do about five.
إنهم يقولون الآن أنهم سيقومون ببناء 5 تقريبًا.
And in most of the world, especially the rich world,
وفي معظم العالم، وفي البلاد الغنية خاصةً،
they're not talking about building new reactors.
لا يتحدثون عن بناء مفاعلات جديدة،
We're actually talking about taking reactors down
نحنُ في الحقيقة نتحدثُ عن تقليص عدد المفاعلات
before their lifetimes are over.
قبل نهاية العمر الإفتراضي لهم.
Germany's actually pressuring its neighbors to do that.
تضغطُ ألمانيا في الحقيقة على جيرانها لعمل ذلك.
I mentioned the United States --
ذكرتُ الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية --
we could lose half of our reactors over the next 15 years,
يمكننا خسارة نصف مفاعلاتنا على مدى السنوات 15 القادمة،
which would wipe out 40 percent of the emissions reductions
والتي ستمحو 40% من تقليصات انبعاثات الاحتباس الحراري
we're supposed to get under the Clean Power Plan.
من المفترض أن نكون في إطار خطة الطاقة النظيفة.
Of course, in Japan, they took all their nuclear plants offline,
طبعاً، في اليابان، أوقفوا تشغيل كل معاملهم النووية،
replaced them with coal, natural gas, oil burning,
واستبدلوها بالفحم والغاز الطبيعي وحرق النفط،
and they're only expected to bring online about a third to two-thirds.
وهم يتوقعون مواكبة الإنتاج بحوالي الثلث إلى الثلثين.
So when we went through the numbers,
لذلك، عندما قمنا بدراسة كل الأرقام،
and just added that up --
وأضفنا ذلك فقط--
how much nuclear do we see China and India bringing online
كم من الطاقة النووية نتوقع أن الصين والهند ستنتج
over the next 15 years,
على مدى 15 سنة المقبلة،
how much do we see at risk of being taken offline --
وما مدى خطورة تعطيلها --
this was the most startling finding.
كان هذا الاكتشاف الأكثر إثارة للدهشة.
What we found is that the world is actually at risk
ما وجدناه هو بأن العالم في الحقيقة في خطر
of losing four times more clean energy than we lost over the last 10 years.
فقدان أربعة أضعاف الطاقة النظيفة أكثر مما فقدناه خلال السنوات العشر الماضية.
In other words: we're not in a clean energy revolution;
بعبارات أخرى، لسنا في ثورة الطاقة النظيفة؛
we're in a clean energy crisis.
نحن في أزمة الطاقة النظيفة.
So it's understandable that engineers would look for a technical fix
لذلك فمن المفهوم أن المهندسين سيبحثون في حل تقني
to the fears that people have of nuclear.
للمخاوف التي لدى الناس من الطاقة النووية.
But when you consider that these are big challenges to do,
لكن عندما نفكر في أن هذه هي تحديات كبيرة علينا القيام بها
that they're going to take a long time to solve,
وأنها ستأخذ وقتًا طويلاً لحلها،
there's this other issue, which is:
فهناك مسألة أخرى والتي هي:
Are those technical fixes really going to solve people's fears?
هل هذه الحلول التقنية ستقوم حقًا بحل مخاوف الناس؟
Let's take safety.
دعونا نأخذ السلامة.
You know, despite what people think,
تعلمون وبالرغم مما يعتقده الناس،
it's hard to figure out how to make nuclear power much safer.
أنه من الصعب معرفة كيفية جعل القوة النووية أكثر أمانًا.
I mean, every medical journal that looks at it --
أعني، كل مجلة طبية بحثت في الأمر--
this is the most recent study from the British journal, "Lancet,"
هذه هي أحدث دراسة من صحيفة بريطانية هي "لانسيت،"
one of the most respected journals in the world --
واحدة من أكثر المجلات احتراماً في العالم --
nuclear is the safest way to make reliable power.
الطاقة النووية هي الطريقة الأسلم لصنع طاقة يعتمدُ عليها.
Everybody's scared of the accidents.
يخاف الجميع من الحوادث.
So you go look at the accident data --
لذلك عليكم النظر في بيانات الحوادث --
Fukushima, Chernobyl --
فوكوشيما وتشيرنوبيل --
the World Health Organization finds the same thing:
تجدُ منطمة الصحة العالمية نفس الشيء:
the vast majority of harm is caused by people panicking,
تحدثُ الغالبية العظمى من الضرر نتيجة هلع الناس.
and they're panicking because they're afraid.
ويصابون بالهلع لأنهم خائفون.
In other words,
بعبارات أخرى،
the harm that's caused isn't actually caused by the machines
الضرر الدي تسببه ليس من فعل الآلات في الحقيقة
or the radiation.
أو الإشعاعات.
It's caused by our fears.
إنه بسبب مخاوفنا.
And what about the waste?
وماذا عن النفايات؟
Everyone worries about the waste.
يقلقُ الجميع من النفايات.
Well, the interesting thing about the waste
حسنًا، الشيء المثير للدهشة حول النفايات
is how little of it there is.
هو الكمية الصغيرة الموجودة،
This is just from one plant.
هذا هو من مفاعل واحد فقط.
If you take all the nuclear waste we've ever made in the United States,
لو أخذنا كل المخلفات النووية التي صنعناها في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
put it on a football field, stacked it up,
ووضعناها في ملعب كرة قدم وكدسناها هناك،
it would only reach 20 feet high.
فستصل إلى ارتفاع 20 قدم فقط.
And people say it's poisoning people or doing something --
وكما يقول الناس إنها تسمم الناس أو تقوم بعمل شيء ما--
it's not, it's just sitting there, it's just being monitored.
إنها ليست كذلك، إنها مكدسة هناك، ويجري مراقبتها ورصدها.
There's not very much of it.
لا يوجد هناك الكثير منها.
By contrast, the waste that we don't control from energy production --
على العكس، النفايات التي لا نستطيع السيطرة عليها من إنتاج الطاقة --
we call it "pollution," and it kills seven million people a year,
والتي نسميها "التلوث،" فهي تقتل سبعة ملايين شخص سنوياً،
and it's threatening very serious levels of global warming.
وتهدد بشكل خطير مستويات الاحتباس الاحتراري.
And the truth is that even if we get good at using that waste as fuel,
والحقيقة هي أنه حتى لو كنا جيدين باستخدام تلك النفايات كوقود،
there's always going to be some fuel left over.
سيكون هناك دائمًا بعض الوقود المتبقي.
That means there's always going to be people that think it's a big problem
وهذا يعني بأن هناك دائمًا أشخاص يعتقدون أنها مشكلة كبيرة
for reasons that maybe don't have as much to do with the actual waste
لأسباب ربما ليس لديها علاقة مع النفايات الفعلية
as we think.
كما نعتقد.
Well, what about the weapons?
حسنًا، ماذا عن الأسلحة؟
Maybe the most surprising thing is that we can't find any examples
ربما الشيء الأكثر إثارة للدهشة هو أننا لا نستيطيع إيجاد أية أمثلة
of countries that have nuclear power
للدول التي لديها طاقة نووية
In fact, it works the opposite.
في الواقع، إنها تعمل عكس ذلك.
What we find is the only way we know
ما نجده هو الطريقة الوحيدة التي نعرفها
how to get rid large numbers of nuclear weapons
كيفية التخلص من أعداد ضخمة من الأسلحة النووية
is by using the plutonium in the warheads
عن طريق استخدام البلوتونيوم في الرؤوس الحربية
as fuel in our nuclear power plants.
كوقود في معاملنا للطاقة النووية.
And so, if you are wanting to get the world rid of nuclear weapons,
وعندئذٍ، إذا رغبتم في تخلص العالم من الأسلحة النووية.
then we're going to need a lot more nuclear power.
فبالتالي سنحتاجُ إلى المزيد من الطاقة النووية.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
As I was leaving China,
عندما كنتُ أغادر الصين،
the engineer that brought Bill Gates there kind of pulled me aside,
فالمهندس الذي أحضر بيل جيتس هناك سحبني جانبًا،
and he said, "You know, Michael, I appreciate your interest
وقال، "أتعلم مايكل، إنني أقدر اهتمامك
in all the different nuclear supply technologies,
في كل أنواع المُعدات التقنية للطاقة النووية
but there's this more basic issue,
ولكن يوجد هنا مسألة رئيسية إضافية،
which is that there's just not enough global demand.
والتي هي لا يوجد هناك طلب عالمي بما فيه الكفاية.
I mean, we can crank out these machines on assembly lines,
أعني، يمكننا انتاج هذه الآلات في خطوط تجميعية،
we do know how to make things cheap,
ونعرفُ كيفية جعل الأشياء أرخص ثمنًا،
but there's just not enough people that want them."
لكن لا يوجد هناك أشخاص يريدون هذه بشكل كافٍ."
And so, let's do solar and wind and efficiency and conservation.
وهكذا، دعونا نصنع الطاقة الشمسية وطاقة الرياح، وبكفاءة وبمحافظة على البيئة،
Let's accelerate the advanced nuclear programs.
دعونا نُسرع برامج الطاقة النووية المتقدمة.
I think we should triple the amount of money we're spending on it.
أعتقد علينا مضاعفة كمية الأموال التي نصرفها عليها.
But I just think the most important thing,
ولكني فقط أعتقد أن الشيء الأكثر أهمية،
if we're going to overcome the climate crisis,
إذا أردنا التغلب على أزمة المناخ،
is to keep in mind that the cause of the clean energy crisis
علينا أن نضع في اعتبارنا أن السبب في أزمة الطاقة النظيفة
isn't from within our machines,
ليس من داخل الآلاتنا،
it's from within ourselves.
إنه من داخل أنفسنا.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)